So.
Today will be complicated for me and for
you too.
In the sense that I want to explore with
you.
A feature Um.
Um.
And it relates with the concept that we
will start today to introduce,
which is meet the program.
And I decided to use F sharp so.
Not because I'm sadic.
But basically because F sharp has been
quite influential PROGRAMMING language in
the last decade.
Now.
Start sort of stabilized,
but for some time it's been a very, very,
very creative language and it started
with as an ML porting in.net.
To show that it was possible to have
functional PROGRAMMING languages to run
on top of a runtime.
Like the.net runtime,
which is similar to the Java runtime,
it's not the only experiment because also
the Scala language did the very same
thing on to the Java platform and JVM so.
Those were the years where there was this
push to have to have to use a runtime
that was not the same runtime of the
language because in the functional
PROGRAMMING language tradition because
there are some operations.
That have to be implemented in an
efficient way.
There are concepts such as lexical
closure that requires special
implementation.
The tradition was that both the compiler
and the runtime were basically designed
around the.
Programming language. OK,
so it was challenging at the end of the
90s,
the idea of being able to write a first
class.
High order functional PROGRAMMING
language that is industrial grade. OK,
nowadays we'll use it too.
Many of the functional PROGRAMMING
concepts have permeated a lot of other
languages other than the functional
PROGRAMMING languages.
Not in the full implementation.
Typically the processes they retained the
typical easy pattern and easy to use and
nice to have patterns without having to
go into all the intricacies of.
Yeah.
Language. So for instance,
C introduces the var so that you can say
var a equal to and a becomes of type int
because it receives an integer in the
first assignment,
which is a form of type inference,
but it is a very simple.
Form of a type inference.
There is no generalization in the sense
that we we've seen the last during the
last class. So in in this context,
F sharp.
Was interesting.
Not just because,
I mean of the language itself.
It was because in a particular historical
moment,
now a significant number of experts in
PROGRAMMING languages were hired by Bill
Gates in Italy.
It was the end. It was 97.
Bill Gates was still a CEO of Microsoft
and started an internal organization that
still is one of the largest research
organization in computer science
worldwide.
Which is Microsoft Research and he
basically did an academic spin off.
So usually universities do industrial
spin offs and actually he did an academic
spin off.
So he started overpaying a lot of
brilliant.
Minds and brought them mostly to
Cambridge,
UK and and there there were there was a
former student of us, Luca Cadeli.
He was has been a great researcher in
type theory and many other things.
There was Tony Hoare,
the inventor of quicksort and many other
things. There was Simon Peyton Jones,
the author of Askill.
And many other Russo, Andrew Kennedy,
Don Seim, etcetera.
So there was a in that particular and it
was a story of let's say 10 to 15 years
where that particular lab started to
create things.
Creating things that influenced all the
world and then as many time as in many
cases that moment passed,
people started moving away and and so now
basically.
Business as usual and PROGRAMMING
languages went back to.
Practitioner that don't spend too much
time in studying the core nature of
functional or PROGRAMMING language
teachers. So I mean if I look at.
If you want to see the difference when a
PROGRAMMING language has been designed by
experts or by practitioner, practitioner,
you can find Perl, you can find Python,
and then the typical thing is that the
practitioner starts.
By implementing the core of the language,
and you can easily guess that it's easy
to write an interpreter in the beginning.
You implement the for loop,
the while loop,
a few things about variables,
and you got a PROGRAMMING language.
So it's an exercise you can start your
own programming.
Language by for fun and you can have it.
And then you don't know a lot of things
that we're studying during this course on
how to represent specific concepts inside
the language,
how to properly implement the scoping of
variables inside the language.
You know you end up writing an
implementation which dominated Python for
several years.
I already mentioned this thing.
The scoping rule of Python was known as
LGB rule.
A lot of global and yeah,
I don't remember for what stands for and
and it wasn't properly a static scope.
There are examples that show that it was
almost static scoping,
but it wasn't fully static scoping.
And and it was just by implementation.
I mean there was no design and and
parallel even worse in parallel arguments
to functions that were passed using a
global array.
So there was no formal arguments, binding,
etcetera.
And this is one way in which PROGRAMMING
languages are developed. Unfortunately,
it looks like that the population of of
programmers on on this earth tends to
like these kind of PROGRAMMING languages.
In the 90s there was Visual Basic,
terrible, but it was super popular.
Then we got Per, super popular,
now Python.
So apparently maybe it's the fact that
typically this initiative by programmers.
Tend to be easy to understand in the
beginning,
so you it's easy to get a traction.
When you go to more structured languages,
things gets much more complicated and you
face a barrier to enter.
You feel that to become productive,
you have to study and so you say, OK,
let's go for Python.
And you have delusion to be more
productive on the long run,
then you pay because.
If the problem is complicated,
there's no way to simplify it by the mean
of the PROGRAMMING language.
So at the end of the day,
it's just an illusion.
But you you've come so far in in your
PROGRAMMING that now everything is in
that language.
You will stay that with that language,
trying to patch that language, OK,
and this is typically.
A story. On the other hand,
when you have researchers,
you may get very subtle things and you
can get very beautiful contracts,
constructs.
That may seem very,
very difficult to face.
One of these is the concept of monads.
So the monadic calculus,
at the end of the day, it's, I will say,
rather intuitive.
Only when it's like first order logic.
First order logic is intuitive to those
people that have understood the first
logic to the rest of the world is totally
not really comprehensible. So.
But.
Let's start.
So I will keep going with the eye and
this will be very complicated for me.
So I apologize in advance because I spend
my weekend reviewing all the
computational expression because it's a
feature which is still complicated to me.
After 20 years and I wrote several books
on that fact,
so I will do my best to make it as easy
to understand as possible,
but it's something that I still struggle
to fully comprehend myself.
So I will try to give you this example of
a feature of a language which is very
flexible, very powerful.
It includes a lot of things of features
that are super cool, but at the same time.
It's complicated,
OK and and and it's nice to use.
We got an example with the sequence that
I showed during the last class,
but now I want to try to explain how.
The de sugaring process plus the
functional programming language plus
other things allows you to have a
programming language that allows you to
twist and change the semantics of the of
the.
Language itself without having to write
your own compiler. OK,
so this is a typical thing that is in
functional programming this ambition to
make.
To to be to avoid to write your own
parser plus compiler and being able to
twist the syntax of the language to the
point in which you can define your own
sub-language on top of the existing
language. OK,
this also as a weakness of the fact that.
That writing a parser is annoying still
today. OK,
so the parse part is typically something
that if you have to,
you will implement it,
but it's really not nice,
never a nice code, typically complicated,
difficult to.
Contain difficult to debug, etc.
So programmers spend a lot of time to
avoid to write parsers because it's
annoying code, difficult to deal with.
Uh.
You know XMLXML basically became popular
because it was a way to not write your
own parser and and being able to parse a
data structure using a standard parser
and and so on.
So there are a lot of examples.
Jason it was.
It's another example that has.
Being.
Mainstream,
and it's basically another way to avoid
the parsing part. OK,
because everybody hates to write parses.
If you don't know how to write a parser,
it's complicated.
If you know how to write a parser,
you know how to do,
but still it's a pain to do,
and so you don't like to do it.
Right, so.
Can you show me the definition of bind
and return in Haskell?
Um.
Manoj had uh.
Been basically, uh, zoom.
I'm interested in the first.
The first definition from Askell and then
I will move on on to C#.
Basically I think that in this respect in
Askell it's easy to to read.
So um.
First of all.
One for functional functional programming,
we said that.
Um brings a lot of value in terms of
concurrent programming.
The immutability of the state has a lot
of advantages because basically you avoid
the race conditions.
It's not the only advantage. I mean,
this is clearly one of the reason because
functional programming became popular.
In in programming because with parallel
computers writing parallel code you you
you get less contention in shared data
and this brings to.
Less locks and more efficient programming.
So functional programming brought a lot
of value because even if you have some
part of mutable state,
you can restrict the.
The part of the state which is mutable
and the rest it's not and you can prove
it it will not be accepted accessed
statically.
So you can reduce the locking operation
during the execution of the code and
that's something that we already said.
In the previous classes,
but from a mathematical standpoint,
if I want to prove the properties of my
code, then if you don't have side effects,
it's much easier.
And it's basically impossible, I will say,
to prove properties of a concurrent
program program with mutable state. Why?
Because the concurrency introduce an
aspect which is non-deterministic.
Because it it depends on the timing on
the IO operation of your program.
So the way in which threads alternate
into the CPU and so the timing in the
execution of a program,
it will likely be different from one
execution to the other and so.
So if you have a concurrent program with
mutable state,
it's basically impossible to determine
ahead of time the behaviour of this
program.
OK,
in fact you can even have some unwanted
behaviour emerging by the interaction of
these things when you,
and this is not the course,
when you study parallel programming,
you learn that.
If the the the the minimum risk,
which is not the only one,
but the minimum risk you you you will
take is that if you read the variable and
then you set the variable without
synchronizing it, then the risk is the.
A bank account gets corrupted and you may
think you may become richer or poorer
more than you you should be because of of
an error. OK, and so this is one reason.
But the the if you are purely functional,
this means that.
Basically, you don't have side effects.
You can try at least to mitigate and
prove properties about your program,
even if it's executed in in parallel.
So uh.
But I mean,
can you give me an example even for an
ASCALE program of data structure which is
which has side effects?
Even in this smallest programmer you can
write.
So what is a data structure that is
mutable and for sure you need it even for
a smallest program,
even in a functional programming language
such as Askel.
Please.
List you can write programs without with
read only lists and so in the list may be
mutable, but in that that's not there.
It's a more basic thing that nobody
thinks about.
Stack or heap? Oh,
that that that is taken care by the
programming language. So technically,
of course the programming language
requires some to be mutable.
Anytime you pass values to a function and
you bind the the, the, the,
the formal parameter to the actual value,
you're basically mutating things.
But the point is that that particular
mutation is local and is only for that
activation, so I'm not.
Writing, uh, in general.
Now there is something more.
Think of input output.
Streams or what is the first program that
you've been told to write the very first
day? Hello world.
Earth.
Where are you printing?
And the standard output is the console.
And the console do the console has a a
state.
Yes,
I mean that is the buffer of the console.
Can I have interference in the console?
Oh,
that's easy on Linux if you start two
programs that outputs.
I don't know prime numbers and you use
the background operator.
You can have two processes writing on the
console and you you will get interleaving
at the console of two programs, so.
Yeah.
That was a pain for functional
programmers that even the purest
programmer.
Did depend on the IO which by its nature
is it has side effect because the the the
stream accumulates the values and the
console changes the value and technically.
If you execute twice the same function,
you will get two different results on the
output. OK,
so that's basically and so at some point
programmers functional programmers says
OK.
Can we imagine a way to have a pure
functional programming language where
there are no side effects,
not even the console?
And and basically the answer was we can
try to hide or I mean to give a formal
definition which.
Uh makes.
Uh.
The uh output.
Part of our function and so basically I
can purely define as a function even the
console.
And and and so the result of this
thinking, I mean,
I'm trying to shrink a very long story in
a very small space.
It was this particular structure and
pattern.
Of programming that is known as a monad.
In F it's called the computational
expression,
and I can tell you because I wrote the
book with the author of the language,
we decided not to use the monad because
everybody is scared by the monad term.
It sounds like academic,
and so apparently computational
expression were less scary than than on
it, but basically it's the same thing.
It's made by basically two simple
operations.
Um.
One operation is the return operation
which given a value.
You can basically create a a monad with
that value.
And the main operation is the bind.
OK.
And the bind is an interesting function.
Now you should be able to read the the
syntax, so let's.
I know about the cabining etcetera,
but let's read.
So if you give me a monad with the which
contains values of type A, let's say.
And uh.
If you give me a function that given an A,
it returns me a monod of type B.
Then I return a monad of type B.
Did you hear the crash in your mind?
So.
When you hear the crash in your mind,
think of the sequence.
Because.
If I have an integer.
Can I mix integers and sequences? No,
I need to create a sequencer of an
integer.
OK.
So the return operation hides this.
I want to create from possibly a sequence
of value or a single value the sequence
itself. OK,
and so that that is the the the role that
the return operation.
Place. Personally,
I think that Returner is not such a good
name,
but nevertheless maybe I'm a tool C
programmer to think of Returner other
than just returning from function.
And and the the the second part is OK if
I have a sequence.
And I want to transform all the elements
of the sequencer.
What they need the sequencer.
And a function that basically transform
every element of the sequence into
another value that may be even a
different type and so the bind operation.
Basically performs this.
I I I have values. I have a set of values.
I I unpack each of this value into the
actual value.
I transform the value and I give back.
Uh, the the the the box of value. OK,
so the the model, uh,
the modern thinking basically allows you
to uh create.
Sort of containers around the values and
then you define the operation in terms of
the two of these two primitives.
And so for instance I can have the monad
console which represents this.
The state of the console and when I
output something I will get back a new
console with the current output that has
been updated.
OK and so in this way I can hide inside
the the monad.
The input,
output and the state of the console. OK,
so this is the route.
And in fact,
there are some examples that are very
famous. There is maybe monad.
Uh.
Where you can basically say.
You can but using the main they may be
modern that you can create the.
Container that allows you to talk about
values that may be contained or not.
So there is just X or nothing and and
then.
You create you manipulate values that are
three more values or nothing.
But let me, uh, skip this. Uh, it was to.
Can you show me?
The computational expression in F sharp.
Or maybe.
So in F sharp is comments.
No, no.
In F# so now I am asking the to create
the.
So as you can see,
the A I knows that rather well all these
things.
So you can if you know the things you can,
you can ask and you can play as as long
as you think you fully understood this
thing.
Um.
I don't know on there how you managed to
fully understand Mona, but I I had met.
I oh OK oh right. We took I got it. No,
I mean that.
So there are,
you know that every subject has a several
levels of of understanding. OK,
so it's fairly easy to understand the
sequence and things, the console,
etcetera. At some point I say, OK,
let's meet, let's develop my own.
Monad.
And at that point you hear crash in your
mind, say, OK,
I have to go back and stop it.
I I I do actually I I found my my line.
In the distribution monitor that will
that we will discuss by the end of this
difficult class. Let's start.
Why did I start with Askle?
Because Askle basically introduced a
function and an operator.
You may have guessed that this is the
definition of an operator and so.
In the application there we are you say
access.
Stream F and this is the definition. OK,
so in F sharp things were more
interesting in many ways,
so because they introduced the
de-sugaring in the language so.
Uh,
this idea of the monitor is not just
built around the an operator and a
function return in binder, but.
Uh,
you define a type with several Uh methods.
Of course the first two methods are
return and bind.
But there are some other methods that
allows for supporting the programming
language in creating a new syntax.
So the maybe builder is a type and is is
is equivalent to the.
Lisa.
Um, but basically here you use the syntax.
So there is a is a type type in in in F
sharp is like a class in.
In C# here there is the implicit
constructor.
So basically you say there is an empty
constructor. That's it.
Member is the keyword that allows you to
introduce the name of a.
A method or a field in the class.
This under score we learn that is I don't
want to give a name.
OK and this is because this member is a
method.
You you may think this under score as the
this argument. OK,
so this dot returning it refers to the
fact that it is you need this this
element in the language.
And of course this is a function even
though it's a a method of the class maybe
builder,
so it's not using the this reference.
And so you say I don't want to give a
name to this reference and the function
return X simply return some X.
Single line. It's complicated bind so the.
Now.
I'm basically have.
Let's go back.
This is the signature of the operation
bind and it's an abstract concept.
If I have a value,
a monad of a certain value and you give
me a function that given the value give
me.
Back another morning.
Containing a different value,
then I can apply the binder so.
This is the implementation of the bind
for this particular monad,
which is the maybe monad.
So we know that the bind should take.
Uh, monadic value.
And the function that should be applied
to that. OK, so if.
OPT, which is the first argument,
which if you remember is M of A.
So.
If OPT is like some V.
This is a a more sophisticated form of
pattern matching.
If you remember,
with tuples you basically give a names by
giving the structure during the
assignment and and and and then you you
do a match.
So if the structure has this form,
name the first argument like this,
the second argument like this.
If it's nested, you can go nest,
but actually the language supports even a
a match operation that allows you to do
more sophisticated things.
So if OPT is like some V, so some.
E.
Is a label. It is defined somewhere.
It's part of the language. V is a value.
OK,
so some V sum is a label and V is a value,
so it's a variable.
Value.
Then so if I have some V then apply
return the result of applying the
function to the V value.
I have a value. I apply.
I don't have a value I return now.
So in this way I can basically create an
execution of something that until you
have some value, you apply the function.
If you don't have a value, you do nothing.
Let me skip the combine.
For instance is the column.
It allows you to to say OK if I have a
monad A and a monad B.
So if A is none, result is none.
If I have some value then the result is B.
It's a a rule to to have the the sequence
first A and then B so.
Then you create an instance of this class
maybe.
OK.
So suppose I have a function that is
called divide XY.
So we can't divide by zero. So if Y is 0,
you say none,
no value because it's not allowed.
Otherwise you say some X / Y.
Easy.
Now I can have a safe computation which
says maybe.
And now things gets more interesting.
This is the lead bang is like the return
operation.
We.
Um.
Oh.
Uh, sorry, uh.
The sugar to bind, I said that.
So maybe let bang is like bind. OK,
so basically here you have some sugaring
that allows us to. I mean,
let's let's do like this.
I told you it would have been complicated.
So let let me let let's do like this. Uh.
Let's read this code,
let's overlook the banger,
which has some semantics,
but more or less. And you say, OK,
if I read this chunk of code,
that would be a is the result of dividing
10 by 2.
B is the result of.
Dividing a by zero.
And I want to return B + 1.
So this resembles a lot like a standard
body of a function.
And when I read this thing,
I can believe I'm living in a world where
A is a number, B is a number, and B + 1.
One is a number. OK,
so I have this illusion of of working it,
but we know that divide 10 to return some
5.
Is that OK? Because uh, divide 10 to.
Execute this two is different than 0,
so I return sum of 10 / 2 which is 5 SI
return sum 5.
I.
And this is a feature of ML that allows
you to have labels in front of values. OK,
so sum 5 is sum of something and so sum
is a label that allows you to tag the.
The value.
And so this is some five, so it's not 5.
Find tells me that.
Even.
The.
Monadic.
MAN function which is the rest the the
the code will be the rest of the.
Of the function.
I give you the another monad in return.
So let me can you the sugar safer
computation so.
Let us come help from home.
Yes.
Off.
O.
The F compiler basically transform.
This syntax that looks like an ordinary
functional imperative syntax.
Into a sequence of applications of
functions.
And every so let bang with the sugar to
bind.
And so let bang divide a equal divide 10
two is bind.
And two and then a function was
argumented name is a.
And the body is the rest of the
computational expression. Again,
I have let band B divide A by zero and so
here I find divide A.
By zero and then the function of the bind
is B.
And then there is the return which is.
Return.
Maybe return P + 1.
Where it be.
Is the result of.
So remember that return returns a monad.
OK,
so given a value you will get a result as
a monad, so.
When you do divide them by two,
you will get some 5.
Sound 5.
Will will a will be 5 because.
The bind takes it.
Let me go back.
I knew it so.
This is the signature of the bind
operation.
So if you give me some five and a
function that takes five and gives me
back.
Some as or none, nothing or none.
Then I I return that that that thing.
This is what's happening.
So if you look at that, where is it?
There we are. Divide 10 by 2.
Gives me sum five,
so sum corresponds to M and five is the
value. A will be bound to five.
So I execute the maybe bind divide 5 by 0.
That will return none.
So B will be none.
And when you.
Somehow when you call the return,
what is the definition of return?
Yeah, no.
Oh, we get.
Huh.
Let me see.
OK. Hello.
OK.
Me cash. Sorry,
I was injuring myself in this day.
So I hope that this is the the the
sugaring and I was looking that the I
even the sugar it more so it basically.
Uh,
in line the the definition and this is.
What by substituting a bind return things
looks like.
So mesh divide 10 by two with none.
Done.
Sum a which is 5 match divide a by zero
and if it's none, none.
If it's sum then B + 1. OK,
so basically the definition of bind.
Makes this none.
Because you're dividing by zero.
If I was dividing by one,
I would have returned P + 1, which is 6.
And this is the fully the sugared version.
So I've always been partnered with the
with the MLM programs when you lose the
types because it may do some explicit
that a lot in particular the the in the
definition.
One of the may be that you presented the
opt. What is the type of optimism?
This is a very independently which can be
some.
So there's an independent definition of
an optional.
So OPT is just the name,
but basically you're right,
some X and none are a primitive.
Uh are defined in in C# as a type,
which is the option type. Yeah, yeah,
so then then exactly.
In the sense that there maybe is the
option type. Yeah, basically, yeah.
OK, then you have the main model,
which is defined by the yeah,
so basically.
Because it so if if you use a the option
type.
So let me explain this discussion we're
having with them there.
So in F sharp there is a.
A type that is, uh, show me the option.
Type definition in F# so uh.
There we are. OK,
so this is the definition of the.
I should probably have introduced it
before. So in F in in ML you can define.
Types that are discriminated unions,
they're called.
So basically you can say the value can be
or none or some with some value.
OK.
In F sharper in ML,
this is super nice because you can define
trees in this way. OK,
so it's the discriminated union type is
very very useful and it's something that
you sorely miss.
In Java, C#, etcetera.
So it is similar to the union type in in
C.
So if you have the.
If you program in C, there is the union.
Now in C union is rather unsafe because
basically you say OK,
the value can be either this structure or
the these other structure.
Uh and and and the memory is shared so
you can uh reinterpret the beats in
different ways and it's rather uh
insecure uh in in in in ML and in a scale.
Discriminated unions are type safe,
but that basically are the same notion.
So you you basically use a label to give
the semantics of every case and so if you
if you see some too.
This means that that is an option type
and is using this case and not the first
case in the value. OK,
it's a way to label label values or
structure or objects in your program.
To do several things such as pattern
matching.
So pattern matching is used on these
discriminated union values.
So this divide will return me an option
type.
And the option type can be either none
and then I say what happens if it's none
and if it's some value,
I I say what happens with that value. OK,
that's practically the discrimination.
Thank you.
Um.
So um.
Um.
In F sharp what what's happening is that
this notion of the mono the is used to
create this synthetic sugar.
That allows you to take this rather
unreadable.
Sequence of application which is a pure
functional application and give me back a
syntax that is.
More easy to understand for everybody. OK,
so that's so monad are we said that
monads are a way to have these values
with two operations so you can box around
a value.
Some behaviour and basically the bind
operation allows you to unbox this value,
take the value,
use the value in a function,
get the results,
which again is in a monadic form and
return that and and this applies to the
incredible number.
Of programming patterns,
sequence are an obvious one asynchronous.
Asynchronous programming as exactly the
same structure, so if you use the.
Asynchronous the How many of you have
used the promises in JavaScript?
You used a monad. You didn't know.
You didn't know,
but actually you were using a monad.
If you use a sync in C shar using the
same thing.
OK, um.
And in fact one of the successful use
case that shows how this uh.
Language feature is.
Flexible is that.
Can you show me an idea of how a sync is
implemented?
And F sharp.
I hope this will not bring all the
details.
But it's nice to see.
So if I have a a type which represents an
asynchronous computation,
so a sync of type T,
then I can use exactly this because the
asynchronous computation is a computation.
That eventually returns a value,
so it has exactly the same structure.
I have a value I build around the notion
of, but this value is not yet available.
It will eventually become available.
I create something around this that I
call a synchronous.
Which has multiple states because it may
have already computed value or not,
so it has a state and.
No, I even did.
No, no, I'm not going through this.
I'm sorry. No way. Sorry. Can you show me?
Let me show you an example.
Of async use in F sharp.
Let me show you the example,
not the definition,
because the definition requires.
Uh,
the understanding of continuation passing
style code.
Which is beyond the scope.
O.
Work is a function which has two
arguments, name and Ms.
which stands for milliseconds I would say.
So and here you use the the async.
You see the syntax is is exactly the same,
but actually a sync has been defined in
terms of bind the return and and some
other constructs. OK, so.
Here I get some print F so then then.
This bang we learned that is has to do
with the modern operation.
So what characterized the C#, the F sharp,
the sugaring is that there is not just
left bang which is equivalent to bind.
There is also do bang for bang and few
other constructs to compile more.
Interesting piece of code.
But basically you do a sync sleep.
Milliseconds.
This is non blocking delay because you
want to suspend this computation,
not the thread so.
Then you type in finished and you return
the second.
And.
Using the async monad,
you can say OK A is task B.
Having every second and then B is task B.
This is the output. This is the.
The time.
And now this is an example of execution.
So task K starts on thread #9,
finish and so and so forth. OK,
and in this way you can.
Compose asynchronous programs, OK.
This is not meant to be.
To dedicate the the class,
the asynchronous.
At some point we will have some
discussion on asynchronous programming,
but for the moment it was just to comment
an example of a monad different than the
sequencer,
which is exactly the same machinery,
so as you can see.
The language has this rather abstract
notion of computational expression really.
Above the average to in difficulty to
understand,
but if you get it then suddenly you
you're able to twist the syntax of the
language to a point in which you can talk
about sequences,
but you can talk also about.
Asynchronous computation and and of
course every time you define a new
monadic domain,
the semantics of the constructs will
change because if I do let bang in the
maybe that was.
Uh,
just to talk to to treat the maybe values.
Uh in in this case let bang and do bang
is a a wait operation.
So when here there was.
Do bang this was.
Execute asynchronously this sleep for
milliseconds and wait the execution the
end of the execution when this.
Finishes, then continue.
So it is like await the end of sleep.
Hmm.
And um.
And let bank do the same.
So it is I assign the result of an
asynchronous computation as soon as it it
is available.
OK.
And then there is also the task which
uses a different library, but honestly,
let me strip this. OK now.
Can you show me um?
The implementation of.
Distribution computational expression.
We will finish this class with an
assignment for you.
Until until now, the classes were like,
uh, OK.
There is this notion,
there is this other notion,
study these notions, etcetera.
Try to understand.
Now I think I will suggest you to to have
a run and try to really understand these
things because there are several.
Aspects that are mixed together in this
in this process.
So there is the the sugaring syntax,
the monadic framework in which you create
things and the same syntax for totally
different application domain.
In the same programming language.
Me.
In many ways for me this.
Has been perhaps the most.
Uh, interesting Mona that that probably.
Let me understand how flexible and
powerful is this this thing.
This, for instance,
relates to quantum computing this
particular model.
I said quantum computing.
Yes, so.
Um, so the um.
What is a distribution of values? I mean,
there are several ways to to characterize,
but basically distribution of values can
be seen as a sequence. OK,
so a sequence of values that possess some
distribution.
For instance,
we know that the die 6 will be.
Sequence of values that are generated by
rolling a dice with six faces.
And and so.
If you look at this way of looking at
other distributions as a sequence of
values that have some distribution, OK,
then I can compose.
The values of of the distribution one at
a time, so.
How are distributed to thy sum?
I create the distribution, so I take,
I pick a value from the first die,
then I pick the value from second die and
then I sum these two values.
OK,
so if I start extracting values from die
six,
I will see 123546 distributed in a
uniform way.
The same apply to line 6 and then when I
return a + P then I will get that
different distribution because you all
know that two is less likely than.
That.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Because there are multiple ways to obtain
given to rules 6 with respect to two or
12 that are obtained only by getting one
and six.
And and so as you can see then to the
assign sum can be treated as a list of
values.
And so you can filter some etcetera, OK.
So the idea is.
If I have a sequence of of samples that I
know they possess some distribution in
the values,
then I can take the various samples and
start summing, dividing, etcetera,
and obtain a new sequence of samples that
will possess a different distribution.
There are a number of theorems that you
may remember or not.
I don't know from your statistics and
probability classes by which you can
transform distribution.
The sequence of values from 1
distribution to another by using
arithmetic operations. OK.
Or.
OK,
let's see how this idea of of having
functions that.
Uh, return uh.
Sequence of samples with a given
distribution.
How can be implemented in terms of this
model?
So let's see.
The example.
So first of it, first of all,
we need something that represents the
distribution of values.
So there is a distribution of some value
of type A with a given probability.
OK, so um.
We have the.
This function that allows me to normalize.
A distribution.
I have the return function.
Which returns a distribution.
Of type A.
And the return simply if I have a value.
X the distribution of that particular
value is X,
so the value with probability one, right?
I mean if I have a constant by definition
is the value with probability one.
Bind. How does it work? The bind?
So because the distribution is a least of
pairs.
Then.
No.
This is a nice syntax to declare at least
in line. OK,
so the these brackets are simply say OK
the least resulting by this code inside.
It's a short and nice to have to
manipulate this in a programming.
Language that supports lists.
So if I have a distribution D and a
function that given.
The sample value returns a new
distribution.
So this is the bind we learn.
So for every X with probability P in the
distribution D.
Then.
You take the function F.
You apply F to the to X,
you obtain a new value.
Which is distributed. And so you say, OK,
let's apply F to X.
This is a distribution,
so it's a sequence.
This sequence is a list for every element
of this list.
Eagle so return the value Y and the with
the probability P.
Times 2.
OK.
It is the combined probability of the two
samples.
If I have a value with probability and
another value with a different
probability,
the function applies returns apply to the
value.
Another value,
the combined probability is the
multiplication of the two probabilities.
The normalization procedure just ensure
that the probability mass is 1.
That's it.
Now with this you can say OK return and
bind have been defined.
Then I have few more so the empty
distribution is an empty list.
0 written from simply the identity
function returns D The combine is the
sequence. So if I have two distribution,
this tells me how to combine to the two
different distributions.
Uh.
And and and the run is simply normalize
the distribution. OK,
so you simply create a new distribution
and then you use it.
And and of course typically you want a
number of distribution that are known,
so you get the uniform distribution.
Which simply you give me a list of values
and I give you a distribution.
And you say all the elements of the least.
Contains X with probability one because
are all equal and then you normalize it
because in this way you get one over the
length of the list automatically. OK,
so this normalize here simply ensures
that the sum of all the probabilities in
my distribution is 1.
That's it.
And the ID is uniform of the values from
1 to D.
And the Bernoulli is categorical,
which is defined before.
Which introduced 2 categories,
so there is true with probability P and
false with probability 1 -, P.
But no distribution.
The expectation is defined here and
sample is simply something that takes a
value from the distribution.
And needs you generate a random number.
And you take a value.
With probability and then you you pick
the value.
So basically as you can see.
We we did something which may look very
complicated because we are combining
monadic and probability distribution to
get together.
But basically if I look at it from a
programming perspective,
I've been able to create in my language
an algebra.
Of probability distribution that allows
me to combine the values.
Of different distribution and reason
about distribution in a constructive way.
And so applications.
There are a lot of application.
Of course there are all the applications
that.
Uh,
all the obvious applications uh that you
have uh in um.
And statistics, but.
There are also other applications,
so a former colleague of yours did his
PhD with me and we basically created the.
I'm one of the Uh to estimate the Um.
Error propagation in physics experiments.
Because typically when you do an
experiment in physics,
you never get from a sensor the exact
value.
There is always a small oscillation.
In physics they use a lot of.
Monte Carlo methods.
So basically they create a statistical
model of the experiment,
then they run billions of simulation and
they look how.
The distribution of values relates to the
actual experiment.
So old people,
but this problem the problem with this
way of.
Proceeding is that it's basically
impossible to understand that what's
going on in the each part of an
experiment. So you can simply say, OK,
the experiment is compatible with the our
theory.
With this degree,
with a number of Sigma degrees of
reliability, at some point they did,
I think in grants also they did an
experiment and.
The connector of an optical fibre was not
entirely. I mean,
it was something like less than a
millimetre, so it was transmitting light,
but it was slightly.
Out of socket.
Result. If you look around in the news,
you still find the old news that
physicists found a way to go faster than
light.
Because uh, that's small amount. Uh oh.
Micrometers, I will say,
stretched the the path to the point in
which all the computation showed that the
whole thing propagated faster than the
light. It took the physicist.
Months to sort the problem out because
basically they don't have a way to
decompose all the computations in their
experiments.
So they started working to to understand
if they found a way to go faster than
light or not.
And the the answer was not.
I think some minister at the time,
maybe even some stupid comment that made
into the news, but nevertheless.
Basically,
this is because in the programming
languages, one of the reasons,
not the only one.
There's no easy way to model the error of
the measure we our programming languages.
Are designed to pass around only numbers.
OK,
and it's complicated to pass around the
number and the error value result.
Nobody does.
And then when something like this happens,
that's complicated.
So one approach can be to create a
monitor of.
Numbers and errors and then whenever you
pass around in your code you pass around
not the numbers but the monad of the
values and then when you sum up.
You not only sum up the actual value,
but also you propagate the error by using
the error propagation arithmetics.
And at the end of this process you don't
only have the expected value,
but also the range of expected error.
Thanks.
To the programming language. OK,
so you may think that this is complicated
and this is true if you think of a
ordinary UI program server.
But if you start using doing programming,
real programming, real programming is not.
The the app in the phone,
I mean that is clearly where most of the
money come from,
but actual and real difficult programs
are those that are implementing.
Through the dynamic simulation and that
made a lot of difference in the real
world and these are complicated programs
where it's important to.
Create the proper abstractions in your
program to detect problems.
Just to give you another example,
ENI Italian oil company found a huge.
Uh gas uh um.
Um.
Just meant I don't want that.
In in front of Libya only by doing
simulation.
So actually when you model things
properly,
you run on HPC clusters and you obtain
numbers that are physically relevant.
Technically you may even end up.
Saving a lot of digging under the sea to
find resources,
which has a lot of consequences also
related to sustainability.
So all this requires.
Programming languages that are not Python
because requires programming language
that allows you to model things.
You need to model a lot of physical
equations,
and so of course the functional
programming languages tend to be more apt.
To model mathematics and the ability to
use of the language to represent types,
metrics or computational expression,
etcetera.
Gives a lot of value and in fact in
finance, as I told you, F sharply,
especially in the London,
finance is very popular, but.
I'd like to tell you that in ENI they use
it at some point F sharp because they did
a scouting research and decided that that
was the best programming language for
simulating,
but that's not the way it works.
It works. It worked like I was.
I became an F# fan.
At some point I was involved by at the
time I think it was AMD and I came there
and said OK, let's use F# and say OK,
let's use F# and I think they still have
some code that I did in F# and the same.
By to to violence, so um.
Long story short.
So I hope you now start seeing how
complicated may become thinking about
small lines of code,
because the more expressive you want to
be.
The more sophisticated is the algebra
behind the a simple line of code,
and the time you may have to spend to
understand a single line of code may be
significant.
And you may say, what was the point?
I can use a simpler code and so I don't
have to bother in understanding all this.
And the answer is no.
I mean it makes sense to spend time.
In understanding the code because the
behaviour of this operator bind once you
get it is the same all the time.
You don't have to prove anymore that it
works like it is supposed to work,
so the ability to have.
Constructs that are depending on that
particular pattern,
like the computational expression in in F
allows us to create domain specific
languages.
So subparts of the language with a
different semantics than the original
language that helps us to model.
Useless things such as the maybe or
useful things such as sequence or
asynchronous programming or even the
distribution algebra.
Which, by the way,
the distribution algebra is rather
interesting for one reason.
Uh.
What it is?
It it is.
So there is a theory that is called the
sampling theory in statistics,
which says states that if you model
samples in a of a distribution,
you can represent distribution that are
not analytics.
So technically if you represent the the
list of samples and you brings everything
to that list of samples,
then you can model any distribution,
even those that are not possible to be
analytically.
Represented and so and sampling is very
compute friendly.
So this distribution builder it's
interesting for for for for this.
And all these it is basically possible
only because.
This is a high order programming language
where you can manipulate functions and
everything is a function.
Function can be passed while pass it
around and at the same time.
It combines with the de-sugaring that we
we we saw it it has been heavily used
that also in that in C#,
which is a good techniques to give us a
syntax that is more human readable than a
sequence of applications that.
Sometimes are really hard to read. OK,
so I think we can stop here. I did.
I didn't do much confusion assignment.
Please,
I mean you you will find if you look for
F# computational expressions,
you will find a lot of documentation
online.
Try to review and read the documentation
of the computational expressions,
not because you have to become an F#
programmer.
But because it's interesting to read that,
because it's probably one of the most
complicated piece of a programming
language I am aware of where.
The sugaring, higher order, types,
everything is in the same place.
So if you want to challenge yourself in
understanding a programming language,
this is a good place to start with and.
On Wednesday we will introduce another
form of meta programming in a more
explicit way.
So on Wednesday I will show you how first
how F# allows you to.
Manipulate the program itself,
and then we will discuss what meta
programming means and why it is important
to be aware of,
because most of the world we live in
today is built upon.
Metaprogramming techniques. Thank you.